<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox populi. In plaine English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[15]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99884482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99884482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181346</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06476)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181346)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox populi. In plaine English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>At foot: A present for this new yeare of the prelates feare.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "In Citie and Countrey throughout the whole Land,".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopacy --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181346:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>VOX POPVLI, IN PLAINE ENGLISH.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>bible</p>
                  <p>Seruice book</p>
                  <p>Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>(1.)</head>
               <l>IN Citie and Countrey throughout the whole Land,</l>
               <l>The minds of the multitude divers wayes ſtand:</l>
               <l>There's ſome that endeavour with might and with maine</l>
               <l>To ſet the proud Prelates on Horſe-back againe;</l>
               <l>That they may make Cannons, and ſend out their Oath,</l>
               <l>To ſtabliſh their power, and diſh out their broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>(2.)</head>
               <l>Of this ranke there's many in every place,</l>
               <l>The which were Created by little <hi>Lauds</hi> grace:</l>
               <l>Who ſince are growne lofty, and now like to fall;</l>
               <l>Which makes them through Anguiſh alowd for to call,</l>
               <l>To Papiſts and Atheiſts and all ſuch as doth:</l>
               <l>Love lazy proud Prelates and luke-warme broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>(3.)</head>
               <l>Thoſe fat belli'd prieſts that have Livings great ſtore,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Biſhops</hi> goe downe: they ſhall never have more;</l>
               <l>Their lourney-men readers, likewiſe are afraid:</l>
               <l>That they muſt bee forc't to give ouer their trade,</l>
               <l>And weare leather garments inſtead of blacke Cloth,</l>
               <l>Which makes them loue <hi>Biſhops</hi> and luke-warme broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>(4.)</head>
               <l>And great men would never be counted ſuch fooles,</l>
               <l>As to ſend their Children for learning to Schooles,</l>
               <l>But that they hoped in proceſſe of time:</l>
               <l>That they to the throne of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> might climbe;</l>
               <l>And there domineer, which fills them with wroth:</l>
               <l>Againſt ſuch as love neither <hi>Biſhops</hi> nor broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>(5.)</head>
               <l>Another ſort likewiſe muſt not be forgotten,</l>
               <l>Who in their maine principles ſeemes to bee rotten;</l>
               <l>Suppoſing that heaven ſtands open to all:</l>
               <l>That tend on their pray'rs when the Saints Bell doth call?</l>
               <l>Where in ſtead of ſubſtance there's nothing but froth,</l>
               <l>Much like the proud Prelates: ſo is this their broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>(6.)</head>
               <l>All theſe doe endeavour as much as they may,</l>
               <l>To backe the baſe Biſhops from day unto day;</l>
               <l>The Papiſts aſſiſt them, and rather then faile,</l>
               <l>The Devill will helpe them, that he may prevaile:</l>
               <l>It makes for his Kingdome to ſtand for them both,</l>
               <l>I meane the proud Prelats and their common broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>(7.)</head>
               <l>Agninſt this rude Regiment there doth appeare,</l>
               <l>Some troupes of couragious hearts that will not feare,</l>
               <l>T'incounter this rabble, in miſchiefe profound,</l>
               <l>Hark how they crie down with them, down to the ground:</l>
               <l>The Papiſts and Prelates, away with them both,</l>
               <l>For we will have none of them nor of their broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>(8.)</head>
               <l>And theſe are no baſe ones as ſome do ſuggeſt,</l>
               <l>But of the Kings Subjects indeed are the beſt,</l>
               <l>Indeav'ring the good both of Kingdome and State,</l>
               <l>What ever <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts and proud Prelates doe prate.</l>
               <l>Who for the love which they beare unto ſloth,</l>
               <l>Do labour to hold up their luk-warme broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>(9.)</head>
               <l>Then let all good people take courage indeed,</l>
               <l>So that they from Antichriſts yoke may be freed;</l>
               <l>And ſeeing that Liberties gaind by the Scots:</l>
               <l>Let Engliſhmen ſeeke for't, it may be their Lotts</l>
               <l>Then joyne hands together, and feare not their wrath:</l>
               <l>But Crie downe the Plelates: and ſpew out their broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>(10.)</head>
               <l>Their pride and preſumption muſt needs have a fall,</l>
               <l>Their wicked devices for judgement doth call;</l>
               <l>Their hatred of holineſſe, and love of ſinne,</l>
               <l>Will worke their deſtruction, which now doth begin:</l>
               <l>Their curbing the Goſpell, will kill their own growth,</l>
               <l>Goe tole the Bell for them, and eke for their broth.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>MDCXLII. A Preſent for this New yeare of the Prelates feare.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
